<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Hamel&#39;s Blog</title>
<link>https://hamel.dev/blog/secret.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://hamel.dev/blog/secret.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A collection of blogs and talks on machine learning and data science.</description>
<image>
<url>https://hamel.dev/quarto.png</url>
<title>Hamel&#39;s Blog</title>
<link>https://hamel.dev/blog/secret.html</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.4.224</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>On commercializing nbdev</title>
  <dc:creator>Hamel Husain</dc:creator>
  <link>https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/nbdev/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/nbdev/nbdev.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption"><a href="https://nbdev.fast.ai">nbdev</a> is a software development tool based on Jupyter that feels like its from the future.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A few friends have asked me why I decided not to commercialize <a href="https://nbdev.fast.ai/">nbdev</a>, especially after putting lots of work into the project, including leaving my full-time job to work on it. So I thought I would write a short post to explain my reasoning.</p>
<section id="background" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background">Background</h2>
<p><a href="https://nbdev.fast.ai">nbdev</a> is an innovative software development framework for Python that embraces <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming">literate</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exploratory_programming">exploratory</a> programming. I worked on nbdev from 2020-2023 with <a href="https://github.com/jph00">Jeremy Howard</a> and, later, <a href="https://github.com/seem">Wasim Lorgat</a>. I had the privilege and excitement of exploring the boundaries of developer tools and exploratory programming while working with very talented software engineers. In addition to creating a tool many people enjoyed, I <a href="https://nbdev.fast.ai/blog/posts/2022-07-28-nbdev2/">enjoyed using nbdev</a> for personal and professional projects.</p>
</section>
<section id="opportunities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="opportunities">Opportunities</h2>
<p>While conducting product research, I interviewed many developers from different backgrounds to understand their pain points and needs. All developers I talked to struggled with one key challenge: it was difficult, if not impossible, to convince other engineers to use nbdev.</p>
<p>The following are the biggest reasons that prevented adoption:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Friction in onboarding engineers</strong>. In many companies, there are often existing Python projects, and it can be detrimental to maintain different ways of doing things when a company has already settled upon one way that it has built processes and tools around.</li>
<li><strong>Collisions with the rest of the software development stack</strong>: it was (and still is) a pain to version control notebooks in a way that’s conducive to collaboration. For practical purposes, you cannot perform code reviews of notebooks on GitHub without purchasing a tool called <a href="https://www.reviewnb.com/">ReviewNB</a>. So instead of convincing people to use nbdev, you have to convince them to use nbdev and ReviewNB. This makes the barrier to initial adoption considerably high - as procuring software in many organizations is a non-trivial process involving security review, compliance, legal and other stakeholders.</li>
</ul>
<p>I viewed solving the above problems as potential opportunities for commercializing nbdev.</p>
</section>
<section id="shifting-focus" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="shifting-focus">Shifting Focus</h2>
<p>Jeremy, Wasim, and I eventually settled on the idea of “WordPress for developers,” a hosted site allowing people to create and share nbdev projects. We thought this would be an excellent way to get people to try nbdev without installing anything. The idea was to narrow the audience to people interested in hosting projects on a platform that promoted exploration and sharing, similar to <a href="https://glitch.com/">Glitch</a> that was as easy to use and pragmatic as <a href="https://wordpress.com/">Wordpress</a>.</p>
<p>Around the same time we began discussing hosted tools, the machine learning world experienced a tectonic shift due to the explosion of Generative AI, namely Stable Diffusion. <a href="https://fast.ai">fast.ai</a>, the organization that created nbdev, was also changing its focus. fast.ai’s prime directive was to make deep learning accessible to as many people as possible, and generative AI was too important to ignore. Accordingly, Jeremy placed his full attention on a <a href="https://course.fast.ai/Lessons/lesson9.html">Stable Diffusion course</a>.</p>
<p>This pivot caused some turbulence as we navigated the different priorities of nbdev, generative AI research, and making money. We eventually settled on offering consulting services for everything related to fast.ai in the form of <a href="https://www.fast.ai/partners.html">fast.ai partners</a>, which would allow us to bootstrap ourselves financially and embrace the larger mission of fast.ai (including generative AI and research). Eventually, I found the splintered focus across so many areas to be unproductive<sup>1</sup> and decided to step away from everything except consulting to regain my footing.</p>
<p>Soon after that, ChatGPT emerged onto the scene and caused further shifts in machine learning that were orders of magnitude larger than their text-to-image predecessors. Pretty soon, all of my clients were interested in language models, and I found myself working exclusively on operationalizing them (a skill that I have cultivated by working in machine learning for 20+ years). Additionally, LLMs profoundly changed the nature of software development, especially the kind of software development that nbdev was designed to support<sup>2</sup>. These factors and those discussed earlier suggested it was a good time to step away from nbdev and focus on other things.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-i-learned" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-i-learned">What I learned</h2>
<p>I learned some important lessons during this process:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Just because you love a project and find it useful, that doesn’t necessarily imply that it’s ripe for commercialization. I always struggled to gain conviction that there was a good business model for nbdev.<sup>3</sup> Instead, I pursued this path because I was drawn to the idea of starting a business with people I really liked. Ultimately, I learned that at least one person needs strong conviction <em>in addition</em> to being excited about the people you are working with - not just one or the other.<sup>4</sup> I also learned that it’s important to be honest with yourself about your (and your team’s) level of conviction and not try to force something that isn’t there.</li>
<li>Listen to your instincts. I ignored my instincts on multiple occasions throughout this journey. As I’ve grown older, I’ve learned to make this mistake much less often, but I could have done better here.</li>
<li>Don’t be afraid to pivot. I think we avoided unnecessary churn by steering clear of a situation that wasn’t promising. I’m much more excited about the work I’m doing now.<sup>5</sup></li>
<li>Own your own brand. My professional brand became increasingly tied to fast.ai and my friend Jeremy Howard. I’m grateful for the growth I’ve experienced under this mentorship – but I believe it is important to build your own distinct brand and identity. I discovered it can be challenging to build your own brand when you are working on someone else’s project<sup>6</sup>, and is something I struggled with. I’m looking forward to working on this more.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="future-directions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2>
<p>I suspect that I’m not completely finished with nbdev. I may revisit the project or related ideas when the time is right. I’m excited by the work <a href="https://posit.co">Posit</a> is doing in the areas of literate and exploratory programming, which include many of the ideas explored in nbdev. Wasim has even joined the team at Posit, so I’m excited to see what they come up with.<sup>7</sup></p>
<p>Regarding what I’m working on next – I’ll have to save my thoughts on that for another post 😊.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I burned out several times during this process, but I didn’t realize why at the time. Not surprisingly, trying to focus on too many things at once was the root cause.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>See <a href="https://www.loom.com/share/5ab26344119440a5b70ce4094827d9e3">this demo</a> for ideas on how coding with LLMs might look like, especially with notebooks.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>The problem with the hosted solution is that this is not something I would want to use. I can’t picture myself trying to host code on something other than GitHub/GitLab.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Without shared conviction, there is no glue holding everyone together and people can drift apart.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>I’ll share more about this in a future post.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>I don’t believe this is always the case, but it can be true depending on the dynamics of the group.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>We previously partnered with Posit and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_J._Allaire">JJ Allaire</a> and built nbdev on top of <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>. I’m currently advising Posit on their product and strategy. They have additional projects on their roadmap that I cannot disclose now.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Jupyter</category>
  <category>nbdev</category>
  <guid>https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/nbdev/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/nbdev/nbdev.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why Should ML Engineers Learn Kubernetes?</title>
  <dc:creator>Hamel Husain</dc:creator>
  <link>https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/k8s/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
K8s For Data Scientists Course
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>If you came here looking for the course, feel free to jump ahead to: K8s For Data Scientists.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="https://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a>, known as K8s, is an open-source system for deploying and managing containerized applications in the cloud. An increasing amount of modern web applications are deployed on K8s. If you are an ML engineer, it is increasingly likely that either the infrastructure you use to train, monitor, or orchestrate your models is deployed on K8s, or downstream applications that consume your models are running on K8s. However, K8s is a complex system that can be intimidating to learn.</p>
<p>I agree with Chip Huyen that, in theory, <a href="https://huyenchip.com/2021/09/13/data-science-infrastructure.html">Data Scientists <strong>shouldn’t need to</strong> learn K8s</a>. However, the truth is: <strong>Even though you shouldn’t have to, it’s really beneficial if you do!</strong> I’ve found that I’m often constrained by infrastructure and that infrastructure is increasingly hosted on Kubernetes.</p>
<p>For example, I’m rarely given access to a cloud provider’s console, and instead, I have access to a K8s cluster with some data tools already installed. When something goes awry, it’s beneficial to know enough about K8s to debug the issue. Additionally, familiarity with basic concepts allows me to have more productive conversations with my team about infrastructure.</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/vboykis/status/1596610600511102976">Vicki Boykis</a> seems to agree that the investment in learning this technology is worthwhile<sup>1</sup>:</p>
<p><img src="https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/k8s/course_img/20221212131043.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Below, I outline several reasons why learning K8s is a good idea for machine learning engineers<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<section id="hosted-dataml-tools-are-not-always-an-option" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hosted-dataml-tools-are-not-always-an-option">Hosted data/ML tools are not always an option</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/k8s/course_img/bellman.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A robot concierge helping a scientist</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Large cloud providers offer their flavors of ML infrastructure as hosted solutions<sup>3</sup>. However, there is often a gap between these offerings and the needs of machine learning teams. For example, I’ve seen the following tools deployed alongside or in place of hosted solutions:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://metaflow.org/">Metaflow</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.kubeflow.org/">Kubeflow</a></li>
<li><a href="https://argoproj.github.io/argo/">Argo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://jupyter.org/hub">JupyterHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.dask.org/">Dask</a></li>
<li>etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>When open source isn’t enough, third-party vendors are happy to install their software on your cloud. However, you often need basic infrastructure skills to enable this. These skills often intersect with Kubernetes. While you may not be responsible for deploying the infrastructure yourself, it is helpful to understand the basics of how things work so that you can do basic debugging and troubleshooting. For example, knowing where to find logs or an API/HTTPS endpoint can unblock you in many cases.</p>
</section>
<section id="nobody-is-coming-to-save-you" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nobody-is-coming-to-save-you">Nobody is coming to save you</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/k8s/course_img/superhero.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A super hero</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A typical first experience as a machine learning professional is that you don’t have the necessary tools to get started. This is incredibly frustrating, as making progress without the proper tools can be hard. This experience usually culminates in a conversation like this:</p>
<hr>
<p><em>ML Eng: I’m excited to join ACME company! You’ve hired me to optimize marketing spending with predictive models. The issue is that we don’t have the basic infrastructure or tools necessary for me to work efficiently.</em></p>
<p><em>Manager: I’m confused. Can’t you install the tools you need? Isn’t that what you are for? I was expecting that you would figure it out.</em></p>
<p><em>ML Eng: No, I don’t know how to set up and deploy infrastructure. We need a special infrastructure or DevOps person for that.</em></p>
<p><em>Manager: It will be hard to ask for more resources if we don’t know the expected return on investment. Can you do the ML project first, demonstrate some value, and then we can invest in infrastructure?</em></p>
<p><em>ML Eng: I need some minimum tools to experiment more quickly and develop a proof of concept. Also, I need tools that might help me collaborate better with my team…</em></p>
<hr>
<p>My experience is that DevOps teams are chronically understaffed and overworked. While it usually isn’t advisable to deploy enterprise software yourself on Kubernetes for security concerns, having basic skills can lift a tremendous burden off your DevOps counterparts and make it tractable for them to help you.</p>
<p>K8s are not a panacea for all infrastructure problems. You must operate within the constraints of your organization and existing software stack.<sup>4</sup> However, with its growing popularity, it is increasingly likely that learning this technology will help you.</p>
</section>
<section id="ml-research-is-crowded.-compete-on-swe-skills." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ml-research-is-crowded.-compete-on-swe-skills.">ML research is crowded. Compete on SWE skills.</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/k8s/course_img/crowd.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">An overcrowded room of scientists</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>One of the best ways to set yourself apart as a data scientist is through your skills. Traditional education often emphasizes learning the latest ML techniques. However, cutting-edge ML research is very competitive. It’s also an extremely crowded space.</p>
<p>In my experience, the bottleneck many teams face is not a lack of knowledge of cutting-edge ML techniques but software engineering skills and partners to help operationalize models. If you take some time to learn how to stand up tools and infrastructure, you will be invaluable to your team.</p>
<p>More importantly, deploying and integrating models into services and applications is critical to connecting ML to business problems. Learning K8s will help you do this.</p>
</section>
<section id="your-company-likely-already-runs-k8s" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="your-company-likely-already-runs-k8s">Your company likely already runs K8s</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/k8s/course_img/meeting.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A scientist shaking hands with someone who runs infrastructure</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Just as Python is the lingua franca of data science, K8s is becoming the lingua franca of cloud infrastructure. According to a <a href="https://www.cncf.io/reports/cncf-annual-survey-2021/">2021 Survey by CNCF</a>, 96% of organizations are either using or evaluating Kubernetes. Furthermore, Stack Overflow’s <a href="https://survey.stackoverflow.co/2022/#section-most-loved-dreaded-and-wanted-other-tools">2022 Developer Survey</a> shows that Docker and Kubernetes are the number one and two most loved and wanted tools, respectively. This is a strong indicator that K8s are here to stay.</p>
<p>Basic proficiency with K8s will drastically increase your chances of garnering support for your desired tools in many organizations. Proficiency with K8s increases the likelihood that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Your DevOps counterparts will feel comfortable with the tools you want to deploy</li>
<li>You will have a shared language in which to talk to your application administrators</li>
<li>You will be more likely to attract people to help you with infra <sup>5</sup></li>
</ul>
<p>These factors make it much more likely that you will get the tools that meet you where you are as opposed to something a software engineer without any data science experience thinks is a good idea (which I’ve seen happen a lot!).</p>
</section>
<section id="but-isnt-it-overkill" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="but-isnt-it-overkill">But isn’t it overkill?</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/k8s/course_img/orange.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Cutting oranges with a chainsaw</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>For simple apps that you want to stand up quickly or prototype, K8s is overkill. Instead, I’m advocating knowledge of K8s as useful when working within the environments found in many companies. For example, hosting your data product on a single VM is often insufficient if you want to deploy production software. Many companies even have infrastructure that may block you from doing this with paved paths that only include Kubernetes.</p>
<p>Even if you are not deploying any production software, K8s can be invaluable in allowing you to deploy the tools you need. In many cases using K8s can make tasks easier. Enterprises have necessarily invested resources in creating guardrails to control costs and security. Those guardrails are increasingly built around K8s patterns<sup>6</sup>. Understanding these concepts can make operating within the confines of your company’s cloud stack easier.</p>
</section>
<section id="you-dont-need-to-be-an-expert" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-dont-need-to-be-an-expert">You don’t need to be an expert</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/k8s/course_img/student.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A student sitting at a desk in a library</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>K8s are complicated, but you don’t need to become an expert to unlock great value as a Data Scientist. I’m not suggesting that data scientists become K8s administrators. K8s Administration is a very involved task and worthy of its own role. Unfortunately, nearly all educational material around K8s is focused on being an administrator, which is overkill for what most data scientists need.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-course" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-course">A course?</h2>
<p>I haven’t yet found a good resource for people like data scientists to learn Kubernetes without wading through lots of irrelevant material geared towards administrators. So my colleagues and I are considering creating a free course with data scientists in mind. If this sounds interesting, you <a href="https://k8scourse.com/">can sign up here</a>.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><aside id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p><a href="https://vickiboykis.com/">Vicki</a> is not someone who is impressed by flashy or new technologies and is someone who takes a pragmatic approach to get the job done. When she says you should learn K8s, you should pay attention!↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Each subsection of this article has a picture that has been generated by Stable diffusion with a prompt that very similar to the image caption.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>These systems are AWS - <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/sagemaker/">Sagemaker</a>, Azure - <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/products/machine-learning/#product-overview">AzureML</a> and GCP - <a href="https://cloud.google.com/vertex-ai-workbench">VertexAI</a>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Some organizations have built solutions that avoid K8s. For example, <a href="https://www.bighatbio.com/">BigHat</a> uses a solution based on AWS SageMaker + Lambda and other hosted solutions. So it might be a mistake to try to move over to K8s in that example – you should try to leverage your company’s existing tech stack where possible!↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>My friend <a href="https://twitter.com/_inc0_">Michał Jastrzębski</a>, who specializes in ML infrastructure, has shared the following colorful anecdote with me: “when I hear Data Scientists shouldn’t learn K8s”, I hear “DevOps needs to learn Airflow”.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>Specifically, K8s concepts that are relevant are namespaces, labels and RBAC.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</aside></div> ]]></description>
  <category>K8s</category>
  <guid>https://hamel.dev/blog/posts/k8s/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/1483922/209075410-b31ad913-282c-4619-87ad-3a7679e92baf.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
